[Music]
good evening
and good day how are you doing all i
hope you're doing well
uh welcome to the new episode today we
are dealing with
uh geopolitics and world history
and as always you have asked me a bunch
of wonderful questions and i have picked
a few of these
so uh like i keep saying uh geopolitics
is a sport it is a sport in which
the ultimate objective is
basically the control of the world the
prize is the world it is global
domination it is the pursuit of
of uh the the world's resources
it's the pursuit of power it's the
pursuit of influence and
there are no rules you make up the rules
as you go if you are a powerful country
you get to set the rules
if you are not a powerful country
you have to follow the rules rules that
others set
so that is what geopolitics is about
it's about the pursuit of the national
interest
on a global scale in the competition
with other nations
that are there on the global stage so
that's what geopolitics is
and it is closely related to history
because every geopolitical issue
has its root in historical
events so that's why these two uh topics
are a good fit to go together
so that's what we'll talk about today
and as always i have picked a number of
questions that you people have asked in
the comments
but let me start with an interesting
question that i've got on the live chat
so let us begin with this
question by hussein so hussein asks what
could have been done
to avoid the breakup of india in 1947
do the stooges who helped break india
and massacre indians deserve to be
called
leaders that's a great question
so what should have been done to uh
to avoid the br so what should have been
done in 1947
as we know india and pakistan were
separated into two pieces by the british
pakistan achieved was was given its
independence
on the 14th of august 1947 india got its
independence one day later
and that's how it was done uh because
until then india was a dominion
of the of the of britain and if india
had got the
independence first then it could have it
could have refused
to recognize the independence of
pakistan so that's why pakistan was
given independence one day before india
so this is what the british engineered
with the help of stooges right
so what should actually have been done
is that the british basically had no
business partitioning india when they
were leaving india
what should have been done was that they
should have we should have insisted
that they leave india and once india
became independent
india should have held a nationwide
referendum
so like i have explained in the previous
episode the 1946 election was
not a referendum it cannot be construed
to
be to be a referendum it was simply an
election for
assembly so there should have been a
fresh referendum under
an indian election commission
a free and fair election without any
british
interference and this referendum should
have
only had one question do the people of
india desire the breakup of india
or not yes or no that's it and the
entire population has to be consulted
you cannot have a separate vote for a
certain
religion a separate word for different
religion that way it has to be
the will of the entire nation put
together
so that should have been done and
whatever was the result of that
referendum
should have been respected i understand
that there were many people in india
who were politically motivated to create
a separate to to
break up the country and create a
separate nation of pakistan so
there was definitely the possibility of
a civil war
well if there is such a such a such a
situation it has to be dealt with
maybe there could have been a civil war
well that's something you have to
pass through and and resolve the problem
like abraham lincoln chose to do he
chose to go to war instead of allowing
his nation to break up
and the war was the war basically
resolved the matter of what what was to
be the future of the country so maybe
that could have been
something that india might also have had
to do well if you have to do it you have
to do it
that's what leaders have to do they have
to take tough decisions
so what india needed in 1947
was a truly nationalistic leader or a
bunch of leaders
who who basically put the national
interest over the interests
of the british because the british
desired india's partition
in order to continue playing a
geopolitical role in the region
right so that's what india needed it's
always
a question of leadership right so if you
had somebody like subhash bose
who was the tallest leader at the time
he
he was but he was not he was basically
marginalized
if he had not been marginalized he would
probably
never have allowed the partition of
india and this entire
two-nation theory that hindus and
muslims can't live together
that is entirely a political creation
under subhash chandra bose
hindus muslim sikhs buddhists everyone
lived together fought together and died
together for their country
for their motherland right so and
whatever
hindu muslim issues exist in the country
today in india
these are again politically created and
politically motivated because
politicians need conflict in order to
gain votes
if the country is at peace then they
actually have to do some development
so politicians keep this issue uh
simmering and and erupting from time to
time
so this issue could have been resolved
easily we needed a strong
leader and that's the one thing we have
lacked in the past
thousand years a strong leader who could
unify the country
with the force of his or her will and
take it forward
so that is what india awaits leadership
strong
leadership a person who can unify this
country
well that is that is a person that will
be essentially see we have had very few
people like that
we have had uh lord ram lord krishna
we have had some emperors like
chandragupta maurya
and ganeshka and the various gupta
emperors
we also had the cholas who almost did
that who did who did it
further east and they unified india with
southeast asia etc
so you need leaders of that stature
to properly take a country like india
forward in the correct direction so
india
needs leadership on that scale and that
is what india
does 100 lack today so that's what
should have been done
and those people those stooges who
helped break up india and massacre the
people of india
do not deserve to be called leaders they
need to be exposed we need to
basically we need to re-evaluate
these so-called leaders role
in what in in the events that led up to
1947 right
the people who are on our banknotes
today we really need to
take a fresh look at their their actions
right
so that's something that will happen
sooner or later it's the process is
beginning
so very good question hussein thank you
for asking this
now i get into the questions that you
people have asked all of you my friends
in the comments in my videos so let's
get with uh start with that
with question number one
and uh let me where is this question
one second okay let's remove this
okay rahul asks
will india ever be able to reclaim the
parts of pok and aksai chin
if yes then can it be said that india is
a superpower
okay let's take a look at our trusty old
map because
that's what helps us understand the
situation so this here is
india as we all know this is where we
are
p okay and aksai chin so if you can see
this here region if you can see my mouse
pointer
is essentially roughly p okay pakistan
occupied jammu and kashmir
and aksai chin is this here region
which is currently illegally occupied by
china
so these are the two regions we are
talking about so the question is
will india ever be able to reclaim the
parts of poke and axa chin
and if yes can india be said to be
a superpower so my answer to this
it's a paradoxical answer if
india only has the ambition
of reclaiming pok and aksai chin
then india will never be in the league
of superpowers
and on the other hand if
or when india in the future becomes a
superpower
aksai chin and pok will have long ceased
to be a problem
you see that's the paradox a nation
who has such small ambition as to
reclaim the little fragments of
territory
others have taken from it in the past if
you have such a small
amount of ambition you will never ever
be a superpower
and if one day india does become a
superpower it means that india's
influence military cultural economic etc
will extend so far beyond its borders
that poke and exchange would have become
part of india long before india reaches
the superpower status
okay so that is the deal if you
if india what is the definition of a
superpower
the definition of a superpower let's
look at the map again
the definition of a superpower is a
nation
that is able to impose its
will across the world whether it's
through economic means military means
cultural means etc
it's able to impose its will on the
entire world
at a moment's notice at an hour's notice
it can
affect the
happenings throughout the world or on
on demand so that is the meaning of a
superpower
if india recaptures these little bits of
territory do you think it's
it deserves to be called a superpower no
india deserves to be called a superpower
when it is able to influence
the globe in a variety of ways it
economically militarily culturally
civilizationally etc so that's when
india can be called a superpower
so if india i think india can become a
superpower in the next 20 years
okay india can india has the incredible
potential
india has everything it needs india has
the energy
the people the the talent the brilliance
the youth
and the potential to become a superpower
in as little as 20 years
okay so india needs to have more
ambition than reclaiming those little
fragments of territory
india needs to think much bigger i think
it's possible
but let's see how things go
okay why has uh this is by nom
why has china remained unified in one
empire
an ethnic group while europe and india
fragmented into rival kingdoms despite
the roman
and mauryan empire so you see the thing
is
that china it is a myth
that china has always been one unified
nation or one unified empire or one
unified ethnic group
the han chinese are the dominant people
inside
china today let's take a look at the map
of china
so here we are to our east is china this
here is china
so throughout the history of china china
has been at war with itself china has
always had competing
dynasties competing kingdoms competing
empire china has always been at war with
itself the present day map of china does
not reflect the true
reality of china's history this entire
region if you can see
my mouse pointer uh tibet and uh
so-called xinjiang
singh it is not chinese territory
historically it has never
been this region south of mongolia which
is actually historically part of
mongolia
has been absorbed by china in the last
70 80 90 years
and again east of china the region of
hyeong jiang
and manchuria etc doesn't really belong
to china historically
so this is what china has achieved this
is essentially the largest china has
ever been
under and that too under one political
dispensation under one
regime but historically china has been a
fragmented nation
it is home to many many minor minority
ethnic groups
which are basically subsumed under this
overwhelming
overpowering han culture and supremacy
so we have to understand what china
really is china this is an accident of
history
that china is of this shape and size
today china has always
had trouble it has always been
fragmented it has had
rebellion after rebellion civil war
after civil war incredibly
brutal civil wars my friend i can give
you some examples for example you had
the anne luchan rebellion
in the 8th century i think about 36
million
chinese died in that it was a civil war
within china
right you had the uh transition from the
ming
to the king dynasties in the 17th
century at least 25 30 million chinese
died
in that conflict again a civil war you
had the taiping rebellion
in the middle of the 19th century
between 50 to 100 million chinese died
at the hands of their own country people
and again
in the 18th in the 19th century you had
the dungan revolt
in which 10 to 20 million chinese died
at the hands of their own
country people china has always
throughout history over the past two and
a half thousands of history
being a nation a culture of civilization
a people that has been at war with
itself
again and again and again repeatedly
so please understand this image that is
projected today
by the media and by hollywood and by
china itself
the china has always been this enormous
empire that is
a myth okay
china has had what's called dynastic
cycles
repeated cycles of ups and downs ups and
downs and civil war after civil war
so the answer to your question is this
is a myth china has
never had a long period of stability
where it is completely unified it's
always had trouble
and civil wars
akash asks alaska was a part of russia
why did russia sell it to the americans
and do they feel
tricked or distressed now because of
this decision
let's take a look at the map
do you know where alaska is
so alaska let's go eastwards
so this okay let's look here this is
russia as you know
this if you can see my mouse pointer is
moscow
in the past saint petersburg or
petrograd was the capital of russia
and this is the entirety of russia today
and if you go east eastwards then you
have the
bering sea the aleutian strait etc and
you have alaska here
this here alaska is in the north
western corner of the continent of north
america and alaska belongs to
the united states of america it's the
50th
state of the united states or whatever
number it is it is one of the 50 states
of the united states
this is alaska so what is the history of
alaska
so in the 16th century onwards the
russians
started conquering siberia the russian
empire
this sybil the region of siberia was at
the time
held by various turkic
kings and uh these essentially were
various descendants
of chinggis khan and and offshoots of
the
once mighty mongol empire so the
russians started the russian empire
started conquering siberia siberia is
all this entire region
in northern asia so they started
conquering siberia
and they started pushing eastwards and
soon they reached
the pacific ocean and they pushed on
eastwards
and it was a guy called bering who
crossed the bering strait
right this year region bedding strait
it's called the bering strait
and he with a bunch of explorers
made his way into alaska so alaska
became a russian
territory and in the 18th century early
18th century
the russians made their way all the way
down south to california
and they even had a couple of uh bases
trading bases and ports etc in
california itself
so that was the russian presence in
alaska historically and
in north america at the time in the 17th
18th 19th centuries etc especially the
17th and 18th century
uh centuries the region of north america
was under a great deal of dispute
you had the british you had the french
you also had some spanish
footprint in this region and this was
all up for grabs this entire continent
was up for
for grabs and the russians were in the
mix
now in the middle of the 19th century
the russians
entered into a conflict called the
crimean war
it was in the 1850s early 1850s
it was russia against france britain and
the ottoman empire
and the russians lost this war
the crimean war and basically
after that their position became quite
untenable in north america
and the british had a strong presence in
north america and the british
were at war with the russians
and basically russia was overstretched
it was so far from saint petersburg
alaska
that it was difficult to defend the
place
right even though it was rich in natural
resources
and it looked for a time to russia that
they would lose the territory entirely
altogether so they hatched a plan to
sell this territory to the united states
but what happened was that the united
states went to war with itself in the
i think in 1851 civil war the u.s civil
war
which lasted about five years or so yeah
and
after the civil war ended the russians
again made the proposal
and the americans decided to buy this
territory for a
nominal price right so it was bought for
about
i think seven million dollars or
something like that
in today's money it's about 133 million
dollars of 20 20
so it was a very nominal price it was
just to get rid of the territory
and so this was in the i think in the
1850s or 1860s that this
sale was done and at the time even the
many of the americans were against the
sale because they thought it's a frozen
place there's nothing to there's nothing
there's no real value in there
and how wrong were they because very
soon you had the klondike
gold rush in alaska in the late
19th century an immense amount of gold
was discovered there
and now you know that there's a great
deal of coal there's oil
and there are so many natural resources
timber and all so this
territory is incredibly valuable do you
know one thing
if you live in the state of alaska in
the united states if you're a citizen of
the u.s and you live in the in the state
alaska
you don't have to pay income tax it is
so rich the state that you don't have to
pay income tax if you live there if
you're a resident
and you don't even have sales tax there
that's how incredibly rich
resource rich this state is so this is
the reason why the russians sold it to
the americans because they were
overstretched and they were on the verge
of losing the territory
to the british so they sold it off
but yes i can imagine how
how distressed or distressed they would
feel today
at losing such a valuable piece of real
estate
right but they were not tricked into it
they did it of their own volition both
sides
decided this decided to do this
transaction together
and yes of course if russia had a choice
today
they would definitely want to retain the
territory
but well that's it's all a part of
history now
so that's how the sale of alaska to
america happened
it's definitely an incredibly valuable
piece of territory it's a very strategic
piece of piece of territory
the americans use it to keep an eye on
the russians there there are many
military bases as well
so that is the history uh there is no
trickery in it but yeah definitely it
was a great deal for the americans and a
very
unfortunate thing for the russians that
they had to divest themselves of this
wonderful and beautiful place
okay kalpak asks please give a brief
introduction on native american history
and the causes for their loss at the la
at the hands of the colonialists
let's go back to the map so the native
americans are the people who have
traditionally been the true
owners of north america as well as south
america
so let's just talk about north america
because the story in south america is
more or less the same
so when the age of colonialism
started the vatican the church
uh basically gave the the
uh colonizers the blanche that you can
go and
claim any territory that's not occu
that's not in which christians don't
live
so that was basically declared to be
which means no man's land no man's
property so even if you have
non-christians living there
it's no no man's property and you can go
and plunder the land
and take it over and and and basically
uh acquire it for yourself and you can
basically enslave
the natives if they are not christians
and that's what happened the spanish
made their way into the americas first
then you had the americans you had i
mean sorry the british
the spanish the british and various
other nations france also had a big
claim in in north america and like i
mentioned the russians as well to a
certain extent
and what happened was that the natives
of the land
unfortunately suffered the most they
basically had no rights
they did not even get citizenship until
the early 20th century or thereabouts
roughly okay in their own land
in their own country so the reason of so
they had they have
been living the native americans have
been living
in north america and south america for
tens of thousands of years
so for a very long time you had this
cahokia first
dogma among historians which said that
the native americans
reached america only about 13 or 14
000 years ago by crossing the sea bridge
which was once frozen
during the last ice age from asia
so that is the dogma that was prevalent
for a very long time
and they refused to entertain any other
competing
alternative hypothesis or theory despite
archaeological evidence showing
the presence of humans in the americas
long before 13 000 years ago so today it
is known that americans that native
americans may have been
present in these two continents for over
a hundred thousand years it's becoming
increasingly uh likely that that's the
actual scenario
so these people have been living in this
continent let's just talk about north
right now
they've been living here for it looks
like more than a hundred thousand years
so this is their land it's their
ancestral land it's where they have
lived for a very very long time they are
the true
natives of the land and their culture
has been a shamanic animistic
polytheist culture right
the same principles that you see in any
other polytheistic culture
the worship of nature the worship of the
land the worship of
trees and animals and spirits and
ancestors in various gods and deities
that is typical polytheism it's very
similar to
shamanism or tangerism or various other
polytheistic religions including
the culture the cultures of india the
indigenous native cultures of india
so this is the same thing that you find
in north america in various forms
and it is um it is a trait
of polytheistic cultures that they are
never expansionist to a great degree
right and they live in harmony with
nature
and more or less in harmony with each
other so different tribes won't really
uh do acts of shocking brutality against
each other there will be warfare and
conflict but it will all be
in a reasonably civilized manner you
will have wars you will have battles but
no barbarism no brutality of extreme
kinds and all
so these guys these native americans
lived this
reasonably peaceful life for for for
centuries for thousands of years
millennia
until these colonialists came on the
scene
and they proceeded to enslave them
brutalize them
these guys the europeans had steel and
they had
new world diseases sorry old world
diseases
diseases that came from eurasia that the
native americans had no exposure to
and they were deliberately infected with
these diseases like smallpox etc
and there was a systematic campaign of
genocide i
it would not be incorrect to say that
over the centuries
at least a total of at least 100 million
native americans were put to death
by the europeans so it is a genocide on
an immense
scale and even the wildlife was
destroyed the bisons etc
so the reason so that's a brief
encapsulation of what happened in north
america the genocide of the
natives of north america the loss of the
loss of their land the theft of their
land the theft of their freedom
and the theft of everything they had
inherited from their ancestors
over the millennia and the cause is that
they were too peaceful they were too
civilized
they were not brutal and barbaric enough
like the europeans
so that's what happened and that these
are the lessons of history unfortunately
the harsh lessons of history you can
never get too civilized
you always have to be prepared for for
the worst
okay recently three mass graves were
found in canada since
may 2021 some of them were children's
graves any idea who did this of course
we know who did this
these are not children's graves these
are native children's graves
so uh this ties in with the previous
question about the native americans
so the native americans were not just
enslaved their land was not just stolen
away from them the genocide it was not
enough to
kill a hundred million of them the
european
colonialists and and occupiers of north
america
proceeded to try and eradicate the north
american native american culture
so this is a pattern you see happening
even in australia to the australian
aboriginal people
what they did was they would take away
children forcibly from their parents
and put them in these catholic schools
boarding schools in which the primary
uh thing that was taught was this
foreign religion christianity right
and they were forbidden to pray to their
ancestral gods they were forbidden to
speak in their native languages
they were forced to speak in english
adopt western
dress and they were forced to convert to
christianity
and the conditions in these boarding
schools were brutal you cannot imagine
small children three years old five
years old seven years old going through
such
incredible cruelty and brutality and
their mortality
rate was appalling children died like
flies
little children five-year-old kids
three-year-old kids they were
some of them were chained you know some
of them were put in chains some of them
were put in handcuffs
for disobeying the the priest or whoever
it was the father or the mother or the
nun or whatever
and this was brutality and cruelty on an
unimaginable scale
you have these boarding schools catholic
schools all across
the north american continent especially
in canada
and this was a systematic campaign which
went on for generations for several
generations
and today these things are coming to
light these abandoned
boarding schools when the land is being
redeveloped you find these
these these mass graves in which you
have these little skeletons of little
children
who have been dumped there after being
killed with brutality and
ill treatment and malnutrition and who
knows what
so this is just the tip of the iceberg
this is a
systematic thing that happened all
across north america
especially in canada this is a crime
against humanity
and the responsible parties of the
canadian government
and the catholic church so these
these uh responsible parties need to be
called to account they need to be i i
don't know
what is to be done what is what is the
justice for this this this happened many
decades ago
but the nation of canada and
and the united states too today is
basically living the legacy of the
this brutality and this theft of land
and this
this genocide that was perpetrated and
this incredible cruelty that was
perpetrated on small children so
who did this yeah the canadian
government did this and the catholic
church
did this these are the responsible
parties
okay this is a question from twitter
hussain asks
um as far as human history is concerned
what interests me is how did
colonization destroy the natural world
and wild animals that's a very
interesting question
so colonization see before
when we talk about colonization there
are basically two
main waves of colonization the first was
the
uh colonization that the arabs did
and the turks did which was basically
the same culture eventually
and later you had the colonization that
the europeans did right
so let's talk about european
colonization first what they did was
basically they wanted they became
they became technologically advanced
more advanced than
asia and the rest of the world and
that's a long history i'll not go into
that right now they became
technologically advanced they're quite
new technologies
and they acquired the means to travel
across the world in these ships
and they wanted to conquer new lands and
they knew there are
new lands out there so they were issued
a character launch by the
by the vatican by the catholic church
which declared that any land that is not
occupied by christians is
terra nullius which is land that nobody
owns
so you are allowed by the church you you
the pope gives you the dispensation the
the
permission to go and conquer any
territory where christians don't live
and to acquire the lands do what you
please with them
and to enslave or murder the natives it
doesn't matter that's fine they're not
christians so they they're basically not
human
so this is what was done by this is
basically
what gave them the unimpeded uh
right or permission to to go and do as
they pleased
they would incur no sin from god for
doing this
so not only did they conquer and
colonize
vast parts of asia and africa and the
americas
they proceeded to exploit the land
because this is a new uh of
this is a culture which basically see
before
european colonization happened all the
world
the the parts of the world that they
colonized were essentially
polytheistic cultures and polytheistic
polytheism has one
characteristic that's common across all
polytheistic belief systems
which is the worship of nature the the
idea that nature is
sacred animals have
have some essence of divinity in them so
do plants so do trees
so does the land so these polytheistic
cultures would not
exploit the land and plunder the land
and view the land as a resource or the
animals as a resource
if you even if you see today in mongolia
which is a meat-eating nature
nation they do not waste even
a scrap of meat if they do kill an
animal for its for its meat they
ensure that it is utilized in its
entirety they don't
waste anything and the same thing will
be seen everywhere in the world in
polytheistic cultures
and nature is worshipped land is
worshipped ev even the sky and the earth
and everything is worshipped
in polytheistic cultures european
colonization brought a different
ideology of
different mindset a different worldview
everything
that is god's creation is created for
the enjoyment of
man that is this new thought process
that came in with
european colonization so they proceeded
to destroy and
plunder the land they dug everything up
for
for coal and gold and diamonds right and
they
destroyed enormous areas of forest
for making farmland or for any purpose
that they wanted for for the timber
they killed millions hundreds of
millions of bison
in north america and almost wiped the
species out
and so so that's what's happening right
about 200 years ago or about 150 years
ago
99 of the biomass animal biomass
on the surface of the planet earth was
wild animals
today in 2021 99
of the biomass of animals on the planet
is livestock
wild animals may make up only one
percent of the of the biomass of animals
and this livestock is all meant for
human consumption
in europe and north america and other
places
right so you have this you have
millions hundreds of millions of cattle
cows
and and pigs and other animals like
chickens and turkeys and whatnot
who are raised only for their meat they
they undergo
incredible cruelty on an industrialized
scale they never see sunlight they are
mistreated horribly
and they live short lives full of pain
and
and anguish and then they are killed for
their meat
and so much of this meat is wasted it's
just thrown away
and incredibly large amounts of forests
are being cleared
are being cleared to grow produce that
will feed this
meat industry that will feed this
livestock that is destined to be killed
and that's why you're seeing
deforestation happening across the
amazon uh rainforest
in indonesia and and everywhere else
they're cutting forests to grow
soy soy so that you can feed the soy
full of protein to animals so that they
will grow large and then they can eat
them and kill them
they kill them and eat them so it is
this
mindset that views nature as just a
commodity
it's just a resource to be enjoyed
to be utilized for the pleasure of man
that has caused this incredible crisis
that we are facing today
the oceans are full of plastic species
after species
is being wiped out the uh the atmosphere
is polluted
the oceans are polluted the rivers are
polluted the soil is polluted
it's all done because of this mentality
that the world is a resource nature is a
resource to be exploited
and to be enjoyed by man and
this entire system of capitalism that
you see today is
basically nothing but a continuation of
this mindset
that you can have quarter upon quarter
growth
indefinitely on a finite planet
if you look at the uh policies of
various uh
various tech giants or various companies
like
let's say apple they come up with a new
iphone every year
every two years and they wanted to throw
away the old iphone and buy the new one
right and the same goes for every other
company
electronics company and all do you
understand how much
it how much mining is is done to you to
make one iphone
how many precious metals how many rare
earths have to be
mined for that how many resource of the
resources have to be pulled out of the
earth
to make one iphone and this is done year
after year after
year so that you can have some
incremental
improvements in the technology so this
uh this this culture of everything is
disposable
and this culture of constant excess this
constant consumption
is destroying the planet climate change
is
a tr is a reality and it is all a
consequence of this mindset
right of this ideology of this world
view
that we can just keep on plundering this
planet
so that's uh in brief why we are in this
situation today that's
what happened that's how so much of
nature was destroyed
that's how so many species are going
extinct as we speak
that's why there is so much animal
cruelty in the world
and uh right now this is the dominant
ideology the dominant world view
everywhere even india is adopting this
the chinese are pursuing it full scale
so that's the future as we speak right
now
unless something drastically changes
meenakshi asks why did
julius caesar never try to invade
india well
let me show you a map it's always a map
just give me a minute please
okay it's a good question right why did
julius caesar never try to invade india
so this here is
the map of the roman empire at the death
of julius caesar all right
so he conque so this is the roman empire
which basically
is the mediterranean world the north
mediterranean regions
the eastern mediterranean and the south
mediterranean which is
northern africa so now the green
the areas shaded in green are the
conquests of julius caesar
it's basically gaul which is roughly
present day france
it is this part over here if you can see
my pointer this part of northern africa
there is roughly today's uh algeria
or thereabouts yeah and caesar also
uh invaded uh the british isles
but he did not establish a permanent
roman settlement there
so this is what julius caesar did
he also did some campaigns in hispania
which is
which is basically spain but the real
conquest of caesar are
france or gaul and this little part of
north africa
he did have campaigns throughout the
roman
empire but these are the two territories
he conquered for rome
so that's all it is and even if he he
had conquered
all of this region which is the roman
empire it's still very small
compared to india and it's still very
far away from india so geography tells
you that
julius caesar never really entered asia
unless you count this little part
western
asia as asia anatolia and syria
essentially
so that's all his career was about
he never went into asia it was too far
away india was way too far for julius
caesar
and india was way too powerful for
julius caesar
he would have been he would have met the
same fate as alexander
if he had ever succeeded in in making
his way
to india and even if we look at the
roman empire at its greatest extent
for example here so this is the roman
empire
at its greatest extent even then
in 117 a.d way after julius caesar died
more than 150 years after he died still
the roman empire at its greatest extent
is nowhere near
india right so that
in itself tells you why julius caesar
never tried to invade india
india was never on his mind india was
way too far away it was
too perilous a trip to reach india he
would have had to go through
persia which was quite powerful at the
time itself
and even if he had reached india he
would have been he would have been no
match
for india's military might so i hope
that explains why julius are never tried
to invade india
akash asks why was china not condemned
sanctions
sanctioned or punished by the u.s or
other countries for the massacre at
tiananmen square
how does china get away with every human
rights violation
while the western media and european
countries governments keep
belittling india on the issues of
alleged
minority suppression and alleged freedom
of speech even after india
being a democracy in china or near
dictatorship
well it's all about hard power india has
no hard power to speak of china has a
great deal of hard power
in the form of military power and
economic power especially
so when this tiananmen square massacre
happened in 1989 if i am correct
if that's the year china and the us were
in a
very profitable mutually profitable
trade relationship
right china was beginning to become the
number one destination for
u.s goods manufacturer china was the
cheap source of
manufactured good goods and china was
benefiting a great deal from the us but
the us was great benefiting even more
from china
because it was able to get stuff
manufactured on the cheap
from chinese manufacturers so it was not
in the us
interest to impose harsh sanctions on
the chinese because it would affect
their own
industries and business and economy so
that is the leverage
china had over the u.s and over the
years china has uh
has basically created more leverage
through its manufacturing industries for
its manufacturing prowess
china basically manufactures everything
almost everything for
every western nation right for every
western company
and and it has a great deal of trade
with all these
countries so it is no longer viable for
any of these countries to impose any
kind of sanctions on the chinese
and nowadays if the the chinese
basically don't even allow anyone to
criticize their policies
for the same reasons because they have
so much leverage in terms of trade
they can ruin a country economically by
imposing uh
trade sanctions on on them and the other
thing is that they have
they have bought various institutions
with the power of money by bribing very
many various officials etc it's very
easy to bribe people
even in europe right
well i'm not saying that they have
bribed the who but the who seems to be
an organ of the chinese communist party
nowadays so there is circumstantial
evidence that it is in their pockets now
the wh o and various
ministers and officials and various
european governments also cow tower to
the chinese
on all kinds of issues right
and the u.s media seems to have been
bought over by the chinese
because they have not asked a single
question of the chinese in the past year
and a half during the corona virus
pandemic they have not asked the chinese
why are no numbers coming out of china
what happened to the cases that were
rising
in early 2020 why did you stop releasing
numbers what is happening in china
who created the virus who released the
virus
none of these questions have been asked
by the western media
these questions have been censored
facebook has been censoring this
and various other social media platforms
have been answering these questions
until very recently and even if you look
at
hollywood hollywood basically has been
bought over by the chinese every
hollywood movie has some chinese
character
and some glorification of china so this
is how
china has pursued its national interest
by using the power of economics by using
the power of its economy
by using the power of money and the
chinese started doing this when china's
economy
was smaller than what india's economy is
today so they always
thought like a big power they always
thought like a world power they always
had the ambition of being a world power
in even when the economy was less than
two billion dollars
two trillion dollars in total so china
has always had this
ambition and this uh this outlook
that we belong on the world stage is a
major power
so that is why the world treats china
and india differently
india despite being an enormous country
despite being already a three trillion
dollar economy
doesn't ever be behave like a great
power
right india hasn't invested in
purchasing influence worldwide
in india hasn't developed a powerful
economy
a manufacturing sector like the chinese
india hasn't
invested in a powerful military and
that's why
india is a soft nation a soft state a
convenient punching bag for
all and sundry so that is the reason why
india despite being a democracy in china
despite being a totalitarian
one-party state despite these these
things
the western media and the western world
prefers
i mean always treats china with kid
gloves while
keeping scorn upon india so that's a
lesson for the political leadership of
india to learn
if they ever do learn it someday
rakesh asks how serious is the matter
that china may
invade taiwan in the next few years
so we should go to the map let me once
again
uh share the map that i have here
where's my map here it is
this is the map so let's take a look at
taiwan where is taiwan
this is home base india for us
this is china if you can see my mouse
pointer and this
island here is formosa or taiwan
so taiwan is for all intents and
purposes
an independent country india doesn't
recognize taiwan as an independent
country
india doesn't have any diplomatic ties
with taiwan but taiwan
has its own government which is a
democracy
and taiwan is not is doesn't have any
affiliation with the chinese communist
party
so china taiwan is a de facto
independent nation
china regards taiwan as a renegade
province
and china has explicitly stated that
it seeks reunification reunification
with taiwan
on priority on priority basis so it's in
my opinion
as the strength of the united states
declines as we speak and as
china rises across all sectors economy
military etc
navy especially so i believe
that it is quite likely that china will
make a military move on taiwan within
this decade
maybe in the next five years maybe in
the next 10 years china will do this
when they
when they judge that the time is right
and when the judge that there will be no
resistance
from any other country especially the
united states
so they are constantly monitoring
the declining strength of the us and the
declining will
of the us to play a major role in the
global stage
and when they judge the time is right
they will make the move i think it could
happen within this decade maybe in the
next five years
next 10 years it's a very serious matter
it's going to happen sooner or later
so that's the plan that the chinese have
been hatching for decades
it may come to fruition soon and what
does it mean for india
so china has developed it has built up
an enormous navy
lots of submarines an enormous number of
battleships
there theirs is the largest navy in the
world today it
surpasses the strength of the united
states navy
in terms of number of ships the u.s navy
is still stronger than
the chinese in terms of number of
missiles
but numbers call quantity has a quality
of its own and china is investing
in quantity so if or when they
take over taiwan then their
navy will be free to move to other areas
of the world in other words
the navy will be free to move to the
pacific ocean
and try to dominate that region and also
to move into the indian ocean region and
become the primary
naval force in the indian ocean region
so when
or if china does conquer taiwan they
will move into the united indian ocean
region
and try and become the primary power
in the indian ocean region so that is a
direct challenge for india
and what should india do about this well
develop its own navy
which is not happening right now so that
in short that in brief
is the matter of china in taiwan i think
it will happen soon
definitely within this decade
aryan asks can dictatorship be
better than democracy at the
geopolitical level
well take a look at india and take a
look at china
india is a what do they say a vibrant
democracy
right and china is a totalitarian
one-party state
well in india's democracy there is so
much internal
friction within the country the entire
energy
of the nation is dissipated within
itself
is dissipated internally because of so
many different conflicts
and so many petty political fights
and so many inter-regional rivalries
and all these various divisions that
india has within itself because of
democracy
right i am a firm
believer in democracy democracy
is what india has practiced for
thousands of years democracy was born in
india not in greece
but the current form of democracy that
we have
is a fake democracy it is a democracy
only in name
it does more harm to the country than it
does any good
we are allowed to vote but try and stand
for political office
try and stand for election see what
happens you have no chance
because you don't have close of rupees
to spend on an election campaign
unless you join a political party in
which in which case you become part of
the system
right so this democracy is only for the
political elite it only empowers them it
doesn't empower the common citizen
and this democracy in in india's india's
democracy you have this system in which
it's perfectly fine to be anti-national
to oppose india and to further the
nation the interests of other countries
other neighboring countries right so
this democracy is extreme extremely
harmful to india's long-term
national interests that's the kind of
democracy india has adopted it's a kind
of constitution india has
that's the kind of laws india has and
that's the kind of institutions
india has which are all inherently
sabotaging its long-term national
interest on the other hand china
is a totalitarian one-party state but it
has political stability
it has political continuity and they are
working on the same agenda for the past
70 years
right and that's why they have been able
to make so much progress
so on a geopolitical level china has an
advantage over india an enormous
advantage over india
an enormous advantage over almost any
other country including the united
states
so that is the truth of the matter
dictatorship is clearly better than
democracy on a geopolitical level
it's not good for the people it's
terrible for the people
and that's why dictatorship is the wrong
thing but
when you are faced with a totalitarian
one-party state
that's intent on conquering the world
the best way to fight fire is with fire
so
yes when we are dealing with the
situation dictatorship seems to be
at least for the short term duration
better on the geopolitical level
than democracy but i am let me repeat
this i
am firmly in in favor of democracy
i abhor dictatorship i hub abhor
totalitarian one-party rule or any such
regime
the people must be supreme but you need
to have a democracy that empowers the
people
and empowers the nation and takes the
nation in the right direction
and which doesn't waste the entire
energy of the nation
within itself fighting itself
kishov asks had the komintang party not
been defeated and exiled to taiwan at
the hands of mao
zeitung's ccp communist party in the
chinese civil war
what do you think would have been
china's relationship with india today
would china still pursue expansionist
policies or would there have been peace
between india and china and the south
china
china sea so let's assume that the
kuomintang
had won the chinese civil war and they
had come to power
let's say in 1949 well the kuomintang
itself was an expansionist power if they
had conquered an
area similar to what you have in china
today
then they would have had similar
policies in my opinion let us not forget
my friends
that the komintant which is that that
taiwan the nation of taiman
taiwan also
lays claim to the whole of china to the
entirety of china
and they also lay claim to arunachal
pradesh so in essence
taiwan supports the chinese communist
party's claim on arunachal pradesh
which is indian territory as of today
despite being a small nation and despite
being
bullied by china so taiwan
even though it's a small insignificant
little country it
has territorial designs on india so
imagine if this
system this this uh regime was in power
in china today
it would behave in exactly the same
fashion and that's why i don't
understand
why so many indians keep saying that
india needs to develop further friendly
relationship friendly relations with
with taiwan
we should recognize taiwan as a
independent country etc the first
condition should be that taiwan should
recognize india's territorial claims and
it should respect india's territorial
integrity
which taiwan does not and therefore the
answer to the question in short is that
taiwa
is that the kuomintang regime had they
won the chinese civil war
would have behaved in exactly the same
fashion as the chinese communist party
does today
atul asks what could the future hold for
the 3
billion dollars by india india's
investment in afghanistan of three
billion dollars
after the u.s pulls out its troops from
afghanistan
you know the this is question right
what's the point of
[Music]
of acquiring a great deal of property
and wealth
and if you can't if you can't defend it
right
today india is building a big economy
but india is not building a
correspondingly strong
military arm the question is if you are
building a
big prosperous country with a
huge deal of wealth huge amount of
wealth what's the point of doing it if
you are not
willing to build an army to defend it
right
the same goes for your investments if
you want to invest three billion dollars
in afghanistan
you need to have a strategy strategy for
protecting that investment
so india invested in a country
three billion dollars where it can't
defend its investment
where it can't protect its investment
i am not saying that the investment was
wrong i i myself
am strongly of the opinion of india
should support the people of afghanistan
and bring them back to uh prosperity
but india can't do this while
afghanistan is cut off from india there
is no common land border within with
india
which afghanistan traditionally has had
right if you look at
the pok region this here
india and afghanistan have a common
border the vakhan corridor
but this region is currently occupied
illegally by pakistan
therefore india's access to afghanistan
is cut off
now if india was made this this
investment in afghanistan india should
have ensured
that it regains land access to
afghanistan
in order to safeguard its investment
or india should have developed such a
strong air force
that it can save it can protect its
investor
investment in afghanistan so india
essentially has invested three billion
dollars into a country
where it cannot safeguard or protect its
investment so what's going to happen now
is that as soon as the americans leave
the taliban will take over the taliban
this time will no longer be a
proxy of pakistan there will be a proxy
of china primarily
and pakistan will have some hand in it
and so will russia
and so will turkey by the way the turks
are also investing in afghanistan now
and the turks will have access to
afghanistan via pakistan
and also via iran because iran is also
getting
cozy with this particular gang
so what india has done it has invested 3
billion dollars into a country where it
cannot protect its investment
so unless india in the next few months
does something miraculous and regains
land access to our neighboring country
afghanistan
unless this unlikely event happens in
that case
this investment has gone down the drain
that's the long and the short of it
as a nation how much influence does
india have
over the world maps again sir
maps here's the map of india
you can see the whole of india and you
can see its neighbors let's let's forget
about the world for now
yeah let's take a look at india's
neighboring countries
pakistan we always start with pakistan
because
until now foreign foreign affairs meant
pakistan
so how much india how much influence
does india have in pakistan
the answer is zero afghanistan how much
influence does india have in afghanistan
it's almost zero now it's getting over
tajikistan i mean
we don't even know that tajikistan
exists by the way so zero influence
there
tibet or neighboring country which is
now part of china what's the influence
of india today they're
zero nepal while india has a land border
with nepal india has an open border with
nepal so india does have a great deal of
soft power in nepal
but if you ask today who has
more sway in nepal india or china
the answer is increasingly china
how much influence does india have in
bhutan today is india able to
protect bhutan bhutan from chinese land
grabs
no no so
the influence is waning how much
influence does india have on bangladesh
bangladesh is basically taking over
india right now through illegal
immigration
right there are millions of bangladeshis
all across india so i would say that
there is more bangladeshi influence in
india
then there is indian influence in
bangladesh when it comes to myanmar does
india even know that myanmar exists
does india have any say in what happens
in myanmar
no so india's influence is close to zero
other countries thailand which is very
close to india
it's about 250 kilometers away from the
andaman islands
do indians even know that thailand is
thailand is a neighboring country of
india
no so india's influence is close to zero
there
indonesia indonesia is just a stone
throws away from india it's a
neighboring country
nobody in india even knows this so
india's influence in
indonesia is zero unfortunately sri
lanka
they're still killing our fishermen
aren't they
and and and capturing our fishermen
jailing our fishermen
does india have much influence that
india does have a great deal
of influence compared to other countries
in sri lanka yes
i think things are better nowadays so
yeah india has some influence in sri
lanka let's give it that
and the maldives well i don't know what
influence india has in the maldives
so even if you look at india's near
abroad
the countries that should be part of the
indian subcontinent that have
that are geographically part of the
indian subcontinent india has very
little influence there
despite being such a large and powerful
country
so if india has so little influence here
what
influence does india have over the world
tell me
i think that answers your question
as things stand today india
has singularly failed to develop
any form of leverage or influence of any
kind
worldwide india in the past 70 years
years
has been an insular inward looking
country
we have spoken about look east
we looked east nothing happened recently
we have spoken about acting east act
east
i'm i'm sorry what acting east have we
done
so india just talks india is great with
slogans
but india's leadership india's
politicians don't
basically are unable or
unwilling to leverage india's
incredible strength and potential in
creating influence networks worldwide
there is a skill
there is an art and a science to
creating influence networks
influence is about networks power is
about networks
right and that's what politicians are
naturally good at
and yet in the case of the national
interest they haven't taken the time to
develop these networks
so to answer your question in short
india has very little
influence over the world very little
krishna asks please tell us about the
indus waters treaty
it is said that by 2050 east punjab will
be deserted thanks to this treaty
then what is the solution for all this
mess
let's go back to the map sir let's go
back back to the map
okay the indus river the indus region
the sindhu region
which is historically sindh punjab
sindh and punjab basically and these
these rivers these six or seven rivers
they start
up north in the himalayan region of
india
so this great river here is the sindhu
this is chennab okay this is chenab the
sindhu is here
indus it's now in pakistan it starts in
india it flows through kashmir etc
so this treaty was was
agreed upon between india and pakistan
in i think 1960
or somewhere in that in that time uh
in that period of time it was signed by
our
our our great state statesman of
prime minister shri jawaharlal nehru
pandit javalan nehruji with whoever was
the pakistani
dictator or puppet at the time and in
this treaty
india agreed this treaty was brokered
brokered by the world bank and various
other
first world powers right and under this
treaty india agreed
to give up eighty percent of the waters
of the indus river
uh system all the all these reversed
ravi china
satellite sindhu cetera
so india so sri jawal and nehru decided
to give up
80 percent of the waters
of this river system to pakistan india
gets 20
and the world bank is the mediator in
the case of any conflict i think it's
the world bank or maybe it's the u.n or
whatever it doesn't matter it's not us
it's somebody else
so this is the uh most unequal
treaty in the history of the civilized
free world i would say
and one of the worst treaties in the
history of india and there must have
been some
some reason for it because sri jawal
nero was a great statesman
he was very respected in the world stage
by the english-speaking people
so uh so it's been a very bad
treaty for india let me come back to
being non-sarcastic
it's it's a terribly unequal treaty
it is extremely unjust to the people of
india to the farmers of northern and
western india
who could have benefited from the from
the waters of this river system
i i don't know if by 2050 east punjab or
indian punjab will be deserted because
of this but
well it's so unequal it's shocking right
so what is the solution to this mess
the solution to this mess is the
solution to the kashmir problem and the
pakistan problem
see i by no means i
by no means have any animosity or hatred
towards the people of pakistan
okay the the people of pakistan are our
own people
they are our own blood they share the
same dna as us
their mindset is different today their
culture is different they have gone in a
different direction that is their choice
fine whatever i don't wish them harm i
don't wish them ill
but the solution the long term solution
to india's geopolitical issues
is the natural break
[Music]
peaceful breakup of this temporary
nation called pakistan
because it it should never have been
created it was created
without consulting the people of india
it was it was
created by a foreign occupying power
right
in their stooges so pakistan is indian
territory
it has been india's territory our it is
our ancestral land
that has been our ancestral land for
thousands of years okay so it needs to
eventually
when the time is right be reintegrated
into india
into the indian civilization into the
arms of mother india but the first step
is to break up
this artificial country and the first
step
is to defuse this time bomb that is the
pakistan military
right usually a country has a military
in the case of pakistan a military
has a country an army has a country and
they are
basically oppressing this country and
leeching out all the
everything that's good from it so this
needs to end
india needs to engineer a peaceful
solution to this this problem
right and when this solution happens the
indus
waters treaty will be null and what
because pakistan will have ceased to
exist as
as a unified state so india needs to
ideally
engineer this without going to war
without firing a single shot
and do it in a peaceful manner which is
good for the people of india and good
for the people of pakistan as well
because those are our people too
so that is the solution to this mess
it's not going to happen in the next
five years
it should happen india should try and
make this happen in the next 10
maximum maximum 20 years
so that is the solution to this entire
mess
akash asks winston churchill was openly
racist
famously called indians a beastly people
with a beastly religion
he made a hierarchy of races putting the
protestants at the top catholics next
and so on why then is such a person
why then was such a person revered at
the time and even nowadays
is considered a war hero and an
excellent leader
you see winston churchill was an
excellent leader for his people
he served the people of the uk
and for him his national interest meant
destroying india and and impoverishing
india further
and and basically stealing india's
india's grain and everything and
unleashing a man-made genocidal famine
in bengal
etc he was a racist person etc we all
know that
these are open secrets so why is this
not spoken about
because we don't speak about it because
the indian government doesn't publicize
this
because indian historians don't write
about this india should organize a
conference
or a series of conferences which
basically go into the truth about the
british occupation of india
especially the 20th century british
occupation history of india
in which the truth will come out about
people like winston churchill and all
that
it should become a matter of shame to
glorify winston churchill
today in france they're discussing the
legacy of napoleon bonaparte
because napoleon apparently uh not
apparently definitely
he reintrodu reintroduced slavery
in the french possessions in the west
indies in haiti etc
so this is something the british were
doing too right but because napoleon did
this
he is now considered to be an evil
tyrant because black lives matter
you know what black lives do matter and
what the british and the europeans did
to the black people
is inhumane so yes black lives matter
but all other lives matter too and what
about indian lives
what about the 100 million plus indians
the british killed
and what about the 10 million bengalis
winston churchill killed
it is our fault that it is not a matter
of matter of shame in the west
to glorify winston churchill it's our
fault it is not my fault and your fault
akash or the
or the fault of the people who are
watching this today or in the future
it's the fault of the indian government
and in the fault of the indian academic
system
and the fault of the indian historians
that they have done nothing
to bring out the truth about winston
churchill
so it is their fault it needs to happen
i would
give a proper suggestion to the
government of india if you are listening
hold a conference about winston
churchill
only winston churchill and his indian
connection his career in india
and the policies that he pursued in
india
hold a conference call scholars from all
over the world
nobody will be able to deny what winston
churchill did publicize this all over
the world
publicize it on social media the indian
government
ministries have instagram handles and
twitter handles and facebook
pages put this all over it
right create videos of this and and
publish the proceedings
of this conference right and and make it
available as a book
let's do it and see what happens the
entire perception will change
but india's government is simply isn't
isn't concerned
in in doing this and that's why
my problem is not that the west keeps
glorifying winston churchill
my problem is that the majority of
indians think they look upon churchill
as some kind of a hero
and they don't even know what he did in
india so that's what
needs to happen i hope it happens soon
aman asks how does russia maintain the
second
most powerful military in the world with
just 65 billion dollars in defense
expenditure
per year so the good thing about for
russia is that they did not have to
build
a military from scratch they inherited a
powerful military from the ussr
so whatever their spending whatever the
military expenditure is is mostly
maintenance they're not building more
things
they are actually streamlining the
military they're cutting down on
manpower because today
it's all about technology you don't need
million soldiers you can do the job with
500 000 or even 300 000
and you can invest more in acquiring the
technology and the delivery systems
and and the aircraft and the submarines
and the navy
the the destroyers and battleships etc
in the missiles
that and the satellites and the cyber
warfare capabilities etc
that actually constitute 21st century
warfare
so because of these technological
advances they are able to invest more in
technology they have a very active
technology program
they are always developing new weaponry
right they
they have some of the best fighter jets
in the world they have
excellent ballistic missiles they have a
strong navy
they have a very good submarine program
that has seen lots of iterations of
submarines
so basically what they're doing is
they're maintaining this they're cutting
down on manpower they're streamlining
the military
and they understand the value of the
military and one more thing my dear
friends
there is something called a black budget
a black budget that is
a secret budget that is not publicized
and i think
every self-respecting country
has a black budget so if if if the
chinese are spending 150 billion dollars
per year on the military
it's most likely that the amount would
be double that but they don't they're
not publicizing it
the americans have an official back
budget that they don't disclose
and i can guarantee that the russians
have one too so
that's how they're able to maintain the
very powerful military that they do have
and the real strength of the
russian military is the nuclear
ballistic missiles
they have thousands of these nobody
dares
to even look at the russians with an
evil eye because the russians can
wipe you out from the map of the world
so that is what keeps the chinese in
check thus far
and that's the answer that's why the
russians are able to do what they do
with the
budget that they do disclose because
they probably have a black budget and
because they are maintaining not
developing new things
especially not developing new hardware
or investing
in manpower
aryan asks what can you explain
the rise of singapore after
decolonization and separation from
malaysia
and what it's what is its current
standing in geopolitics
so singapore basically was formed
in the mid i don't remember the exact
time span 40s 50s thereabouts yeah it's
separated from malaysia
the leader of singapore mr lee kuan yew
wanted a unified
state with malaysia the malaysians did
not agree so he had to reluctantly
run his own independent city state of
singapore it's a very tiny
island on which there is one city and
that's what he
governed and what mr lee kuan yew did
was that he was
the de facto dictator of of singapore
and the thing about him was that he was
a benevolent dictator
he is what's called a benevolent
dictator he spent his entire
life his entire career on trying to
trying to uplift singapore
so within a single generation within a
span of two decades less than two
decades
he took this third world impoverished
city-state
and transformed it into a first world
nation
right and he did it by by radically
revolutionizing the economy he
completely revamped the economy he
instituted capitalism let's say faye
capitalism let's say fair capitalism
means no restrictions just do what you
can
do what you want no restrictions no no
no the kind of restrictions you have in
india
upon entrepreneurship and capitalism
none of that was there
right so you so foreign countries were
free to invest as much as they wanted
they were free to buy and acquire
singaporean companies
or or or other entrepreneurial
outfits etc so there was a great amount
of
foreign money into singapore
and by means of these policies and by
means of this iron fisted control
over singapore and these very effective
laws and the very effective
implementation of the laws
that mr lee kuan yew was able to
transform singapore
within a single generation and it's
become one of the most powerful
economies in the world
it's very influential the chinese have
copied the singapore model
in transforming their economy as well so
that's what happened that's what one man
did
in one lifetime in less than one
lifetime right
so singapore was and still is a
one-party state
singapore was a one one-man dictatorship
under lee kuan yew
it was a benevolent dictatorship he was
very harsh with his critics
and with the people who broke the laws
but
apart from that he basically
enriched singapore and he gave the
people of singapore one of the highest
per capita gdps
and the one of the highest standards of
living that you can find anywhere in the
world
but it was all uh it was all according
to
the law that he laid down right so
that's why he
he's thought about off as a dictator its
current standing in geopolitics is not
much because in geopolitics as
a powerful economy is not enough you
need to have
a military strength as well and
singapore being a single
small city state doesn't have a powerful
military it just can't have one
so that's why it doesn't have any
significant standing in geopolitics
but it's a shining light in in the
economic
world definitely
saurajit asks do you think companies
like twitter are being used by the
chinese communist party to create
disharmony in india
if yes then how can it be created so
listen um
whether it's the ccp or whether it's the
us government or whether it is
other vested interests in the western
world whoever it is
social media is definitely something
that can be leveraged to create a great
deal of disharmony in any country
and in india it's definitely the case
that certain people get blocked or
banned me myself i i had
i had i lost 20 000 followers in one day
on twitter
because they decided to cut off 20 000
followers and and so many people have
been targeted like this
people have been blocked and banned for
no reason and uh
ostensibly for for sharing some fake
document or fake news
while some other fake news propagators
are given blue ticks etc
so there is definitely a political angle
to this a certain political ideology
is allowed to have free reign on twitter
while certain other political
viewpoints or worldviews are suppressed
and censored on twitter
so that's very much the case recently
you have a
blatant interference in the internal
affairs of india when
they take away blue ticks from the vice
president of india
and they they blocked the law minister
of india
right so i don't blame twitter for this
my point is why can't india create a new
law
for social media which will regulate the
entire behavior of any social media
company
which operates in india in the indian
cyberspace
make a very clear unambiguous set of
laws
that will decide how what sort of speech
is allowed what sort of speech is not
allowed
what kind of action gets you banned
whether you can appeal a ban or not
everything should be decided
should be put down in indian law
why can't the government of india enact
a law like that
regulates social media we see the the
law minister of india complaining on
twitter that i was blocked for
i was blocked for an hour or two hours
or whatever
the law minister is unwilling
to lay down the law to twitter that
is the kind of pusillanimity we are
seeing today i think it is a matter of
great shame
for india that india's political leaders
use twitter and instagram as the primary
means of communicating with the people
of india
right i i think it's a matter of shame
that this happens why hasn't india
developed its own news and and the
policy dissemination organ
like the chinese have like the russians
have like the us has
every ministry should have its own daily
news briefings
in which in which uh attendance by media
houses should be compulsory
right and they should be uh disseminated
on an indian
platform why hasn't india developed the
platform
why do india's leaders use foreign
platforms
for communicating with the people of
india i think it's a matter of great
shame and i'm very disappointed
so yes companies like twitter etc can be
used
to create this harmony in india and
unfortunately the
indian government is is behaving like it
has no power whatsoever
in its own country and i don't blame
twitter for this i blame the government
of india
so there you are okay my friends i am
done with the questions let me see if
there are some interesting
live chat questions this has gone on for
a very long time today
okay let me see
live chat first let me remove this
question here we go
okay there are lots and lots of
questions
uh world history or geopolitics
china communicates with their people on
their own platforms they use twitter to
communicate with the rest of the world
look at that
brilliant brilliant very good
observation they utilize the western
platforms to disseminate propaganda and
misinformation in the west
but they don't allow platforms like
twitter within china they have their own
platforms
now i am not saying that india should
block everything out and have
closed in solar system i am saying india
should lay down the law
within india in indian cyberspace and
all these
social media platforms should be made to
comply with indian law when it comes to
indian
social media accounts and the indian
cyber space
so good point sir very good
okay some more interesting questions
doreen menden asks today india is
looking for
fdi fbi for prosperity
is there any way to enhance the indian
economy through indigenous resources and
innovation
launch a big development campaign
right how did the americans become so
wealthy how did they become such a
powerful economy
they become a powerful economy because
they invested
an enormous amount in the uh
arms and defense industry they
they were in a period of a great
depression in the 1930s
the 1930s was an enormously it was a
terrible depression in the u.s
a great economic depression the country
was in poverty
and then the first the second world war
happened in the whole country
the entire workforce of the country was
was
put to use in in creating in developing
weapons
in manufacturing weapons and that is
what built up the economy again
after the the fukushima earthquake the
the tohoku earthquake in in japan
in 2011 they embarked upon a rebuilding
program which again boosted the economy
so why can't india boost the economy by
by embarking upon a large scale
uh infrastructure building program and
and arms in this
and in boosting the arms industry we
need ships we need a powerful navy
we need a more powerful air force we
need a more powerful in uh military
right army so why can't we invest in
that it will
create a great great amount of jobs it
will create infrastructure
and it will create a great demand for
other things as well from other
technologies
which will boost other sectors as well
so that is one idea
the ideas are there are lots of ideas
there are lots of solutions
the thing is does the government have
the will
and the fortitude to do this we see the
closure of the sterlite copper plant in
southern india
because certain ngos demonstrated
against that
and because of that india has become a
net importer of copper
instead of being an exporter which it
was before this plant was closed down
so the actions that are taken the
decisions that are taken are all against
the national interest
all we need to do is to is to follow the
national interest
right so there are many ways of doing
this i am not an economist but i can
give some
suggestions based on historical
precedent
right so it is definitely possible for
india to become a prosperous country
and a powerful country in all domains in
within one generation it is very much
possible all we need is the right
leadership
all right um
will monarchy be reinstated in nepal i
think it's
it's too far down the road for that
nepal has changed a lot it was rajiv
gandhi who had the monarchy removed it
was a covert operation
a long-term operation and that's what
india did
and that's how nepal went from being the
last hindu nation in the world to being
a
almost communist country today right
under the chinese influence
so that's unfortunate and disappointing
why is india not a tourism hub because
the government isn't investing in
tourism
india has the capability the potential
to become a tourism superpower
india has so much ancient culture so
many archaeological monuments so many
uh brilliant beautiful pieces of
architecture so many temples
india has every climate every terrain
you can think of india has forests it
has mountains it has glaciers it has
snow
it has you can do
water sports in india there are so many
beaches india has one of the longest
coastlines in the world
india has islands there is everything
in india for india to become a tourism
superpower
why is it not a tourism hub because the
ministry of tourism is a failure
the ministry of tourism should be
embarking upon i mean this can boost the
indian gdp by several percentage points
just tourism itself it can bring in
bring in
billions of dollars of revenue every
year and it can enhance india's standing
worldwide
if so many of so many people come to
india for tourism
the ministry of tourism is a
non-performing ministry it is a failure
right it is wasting money on of on
opening
offices across the world why do you need
to open offices in sydney and in the us
when you have the internet today why do
you need
indian ministry of tourism offices
across the world why
it's a waste of money it's a it's a
means of giving nice deputations
to various bureaucrats abroad so
these are the reasons why india is not a
tourism hub
okay one final question for today
was julius caesar kidnapped by king
vikramaditya's soldiers
the brief answer is no all right my
friends it's been a wonderful session
wonderful questions
thank you so much for your questions
thank you for your viewership
keep keep the questions coming tomorrow
we have another very interesting session
and until then thank you very much i
wish you a good day good night wherever
you are i will see you tomorrow
bye